Records of the Anson G. Phelps Lectures on Early American History RG.47.21.3
New York University Archives
Records of the Anson G. Phelps Lectures on Early American History
1920-2008
New York University Archives
New York University. Department of History
Phelps, Anson G.
RG.47.21.3
3 boxes
The Anson G. Phelps Lectures on Early American History were established through a bequest of James Stoker, an alumnus of NYU, in 1918. The lectures are named in honor of Stoker's maternal grandfather, Anson Green Phelps (1781 – 1853). The collection consists of pamphlets, brochures, and posters promoting the lectures and published lectures and manuscripts used for lecture topics.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically into two series.
Missing Title
Published Lectures
Brochures and Posters
History of the Lectures
The Anson G. Phelps Lectures on Early American History were established through a bequest of James Stoker, an alumnus of NYU, in 1918. The lectures are named in honor of Stoker's maternal grandfather, Anson Green Phelps (1781 – 1853), a descendant of the early settlers of New England. The purpose of the lectures, according to Stokes, was that of "inculcating a knowledge of the principles which animated the Puritan Fathers and early colonists; and of the influence they have exerted upon modern civilization." The first lecture was given in 1920. Subsequent lectures have been organized on an irregular basis.
Provenance
Accessioned by University Archives in two accruals.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the Anson G. Phelps lectures though promotional materials such as posters, leaflets and brochures, as well as printed manuscripts that contain the lectures given or manuscripts that the lectures were based on.
Lectures and lecturing.; American history and culture.; Lectures.; Stokes, James
- Published Lectures
  - The Influence of the Pilgrim Fathers and Other Colonists on the Development of American Civilization, 1 of 2, 1920 December 10; Kingsley, Darwin P. (Box 1)
  - The Influence of the Pilgrim Fathers and Other Colonists on the Development of American Civilization, 2 of 2, 1920 December 10; Kingsley, Darwin P. (Box 1)
  - The Pilgrim Fathers From a Dutch Point of View, 1932; Plooij, D. (Box 1)
  - The Foundations of American Constitutionalism, 1932; McLaughlin, Andrew C. (Box 1)
  - Our Earliest Colonial Settlements, 1933; Andrews, Charles M. (Box 1)
  - The Puritan Pronaos: Studies in the Intellectual Life of New England in the Seventeenth Century, 1936; Morison, Samuel Eliot (Box 1)
  - Yankees and Yorkers, 1940; Fox, Dixon Ryan (Box 1)
  - Religion and the State: The Making and Testing of an American Tradition, 1941; Greene, Evarts Boutell (Box 1)
  - The Golden Age of Colonial Culture, 1942; Wertenbaker, Thomas Jefferson (Box 1)
  - Conservatism in Early American History, 1948; Labaree, Leonard Woods (Box 1)
  - The Colonial Craftsman, 1950; Bridenbaugh, Carl (Box 1)
  - The Legend of the Founding Fathers, 1956; Craven, Wesley Frank (Box 1)
  - Medicine and Society in America, 1660-1860, 1960; Shryock, Richard Harrison (Box 2)
  - Visible Saints: The History of a Puritan Idea, 1963; Morgan, Edmund S. (Box 2)
  - The Dream of Prosperity in Colonial America, 1965; Wright, Louis B. (Box 2)
  - The American Revolution Reconsidered, 1967; Morris, Richard B. (Box 2)
  - The American Revolution Within America, 1974; Jensen, Merrill (Box 2)
  - The Ordeal of Thomas Hutchinson, 1974; Bailyn, Bernard (Box 2)
  - The Old Revolutionaries: Political Lives in the Age of Samuel Adams, 1980; Maier, Pauline (Box 2)
  - Emulation and Invention, 1981; Hindle, Brooke (Box 2)
- Brochures and Posters
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1950 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1962 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1964 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1966 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1969 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1973 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1986 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 1996 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Lecture Series Poster, 2008 (Oversize Box 1)
  - Shaker Spirit Drawing, Undated (Oversize Box 1)
  - Small Items, 1964-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)